foreign
[Music]
black again that's fine
Eagle W12 okay let's play another
Sicilian
yeah Knight F3 Knight C6 but something
tells me we might face
a non Knight F3 move
of which there are many okay D4 so Smith
Mora
C takes D4 of course
okay Queen takes D4 so that that's
that's not a terrible move but it's
obviously not a good move either
this type type of play makes more sense
against E5 there it's called the center
game and the center game actually is
legit but against the Sicilian this is
really just a very poor line because it
loses a bunch of Tempe
it loses a bunch of Tempe why does it
lose a bunch of Tempe because you're
basically playing a scandi with white
and scandi is bad enough to want to play
it with both colors we of course play
Knight C6 to attack the queen now we
should start with Knight C6 right that's
that's not gonna hurt Queen A4
so white is kind of almost literally
playing a scandi with colors reversed
with the pawn already on e4
now here blue black has a gazillion ways
to set up their pieces like we can do a
bunch of different stuff but one thing
that you'll notice is that I like to
play consistent with the spirit of
whatever line I would play against let's
say the open Sicilian right so if you're
a dragon player then you might prefer to
play G6 in this position if you are a
taimano player or a spashnikov player
you might prefer to play E6 if you're a
9R player you might like to play D6
right and all three of those moves are
totally valid e6d6 G6 even A6 to prepare
some B5 nonsense looks pretty
interesting but because we are
accelerated Dragon players in the
context of the speedrun we are going to
stick to the fiancado setup when
possible Right There are some situations
when it is objectively a better idea to
let's say push E6 but this is not one of
them I don't see a downside to Fan
ketoing the bishop Bishop D2 a classic
idea the bishop is heading for C3
but that's not going to end up being all
that effective we can proceed with the
finqueto
and against Bishop C3 of course we we
most certainly do not want to trade
Bishops that would be a bad idea
what we also don't want to do and
actually our opponent might play Knight
C3 but we're okay C3 well that really is
just
I mean that's just a conceptually bad
move because it doesn't develop a piece
and it actually self-restricts his
Knight
uh his or her night and it's I mean at
this point White's lack of development
it has reached uh alarming proportions
but that doesn't mean our Play Changes
in any appreciable way we just continue
developing our pieces normally all right
we just continue developing our pieces
normally and
you know if you have a good sense for
the position you will notice that at
some point we should consider pushing D5
in order to open up uh in order to open
up the center but doing so now I think
is a little bit premature it's not a bad
move you can play D5 now but after ed5 I
don't want to do the same thing that y
was doing and get our Queen out a little
too early so what should we do well we
should continue our development how
should we continue our development by
getting this night out and putting it on
F6 now you might say well I've been
watching the speedrun diligently didn't
you just say that in such situations
it's a good idea to play E6 and 97 in
order to not obstruct the dark script
Bishop right and this is a good example
of proper use of comparison right this
is actually a different type of
situation right why is this different
well our Bishop on G7 is no longer like
the center of the universe right now the
center of the universe is getting our
pieces out quickly and then quickly
opening up the center and in the context
of that in the context of that it
matters a lot less where we put our
Knight and it matters more the speed of
our development so simply put e697 takes
two moves and with the center being a
little bit more open the weakness of the
D6 square is a little bit more
concerning does that make sense whereas
Knight F6 is efficient and it's active
and it puts pressure on the E4 Pawn
I still think it's too early to play D5
what should we do first what's a move
that we should just throw in
we're not going to regret it for sure if
we play this move what am I talking
about of course we should Castle we
should just tuck our King to safety
white is still nowhere near
completing their development so we
definitely have another development move
to burn and now we are fully ready
to play thanks again for the 50 Subs I
really appreciate it this is awesome
okay E5 well white is doing our bidding
for us this is a move that we you know
this this is the move I I dreamed of
seeing because white is totally
unequipped to deal with white is
overextending himself and he's got no
pieces out so E5 is is just you know the
the train has left the tracks a long
time ago but where should our night go
classic kind of scenario right when a
pawn is pushed generally a square is
going to be opened up just
mathematically that's true by definition
you should always be aware of what that
square is and whether you can occupy it
so Knight H5 is good
90 tribe is good but I don't see a
reason to not play in the center why not
Knight D5 right let's keep our pieces
centralized when possible just abiding
my principles of course Knight H5 is
also perfectly fine
yeah not always to the center but in
this case I like the idea of keeping our
Knight nicely centralized although
what's interesting is that Knight H5
does have one advantage over Knight D5
which I will explain after the game
Queen E4 our opponent continues to to
derail now of course we want to take the
bishop
now Knight G4 was also very good
Knight G4 might even be the best move
because it guarantees the win of the E5
Pawn after Knight G4 we have three
attackers and only one Defender
now what should we take the E5 Pawn with
and this is a I think a good question to
really test your understanding in
general yeah we should take with the
Knight very good I mean I
and I'm not picking on people who are
saying Bishop but Bishop takes E5 is a
good example of one movitus right the
queen on F4 is a pretty big liability
why is it a liability well it's a
liability because the queen when it's
out alone with no other pieces generally
is a liability and after Knight takes C5
we are setting up a potential Fork on D3
right and we are sort of keeping the
queen where we want it Bishop takes E5
sends the queen back to safety and as
I've said before you want to be very
careful in general moving the bishop
away from its fine get out square even
if it's on the same diagonal
will often lead to some awkwardness in
this case after Bishop takes E5 Queen D2
white will then develop his Knight on F3
with tempo and when I say with Tempo I
don't necessarily mean white threatens
to win the bishop on E5 white threatens
to trade it and we certainly don't want
that Bishop to get traded so it's more
of a positional threat does that make
sense so Knight takes C5 to me is kind
of a no-brainer
and you're like why are you belaboring
the point it doesn't matter it's upon
your winning either way true but again
we're laying the foundations here and
when you make sound decisions in these
small things what you'll quickly find is
that your games are just so much
smoother Knight D2
so we need to keep our pedal to the
metal here there's multiple ways that we
can continue our initiative
there's this sort of Developmental
approach and then there's the like the
fully maximally I want to create threats
on every move approach we're going to
take the latter approach we're going to
take the slightly more methodical
approach yeah a lot of you are are
thinking of the move Queen B6 excellent
move excellent move Queen B6
but I like a little more of a subtle
move yeah I like Queen C7
and you might say well you just said
that a move like this is one mobitis
we're just playing for tricks no
we're not playing for tricks first of
all this is not an easy move to prevent
because the White Queen just doesn't
have that many comfortable squares but
second of all we are making a move that
is useful
even if it didn't carry the threat of
Knight T3 that is a good test for
whether the move you're playing is just
playing for tricks are actually useful
like if the move didn't carry the threat
would you still play it maybe not
because we will win the queen but Queen
C7 is an excellent move I was going to
say in case White Castle's Queen side
the queen is now x-raying the C3 Pawn
it's helping the Rooks get coordinated
so it's definitely a move that doesn't
hurt but it also doesn't hurt that it
carries the threat of winning the queen
and we do with Knight D3 check
and we do a 93 trick thank you righteous
Judas for the sub
thank you Eagle for the queen
pretty easy win there
13 moves
and I again I didn't do anything this
game I just reacted to our opponent's
threats we developed our pieces and we
won the queen that's it
Bishop E4
but let's again let's let's not give
white a chance to prolong the game so a
good example here of deciding between
taking more material or uh making more
qualitative moves so because white is so
poorly developed here
I wouldn't even suggest Queen takes F2
I would suggest opening up the center as
quickly as possible before white has
gotten a chance to finish his
development and the move that really
looks nice to me I love Bishop H6 by the
way switching the diagonal of the bishop
and x-raying the Knight on D2 great move
but let's just freaking go for me D5
don't get D6 just go D5 what's a pawn
here you're up a queen just give away a
pawn open the D file right this is gonna
lead to Victory so much faster now what
has been the effect of opening up the
default well now we can put a rook on d8
and this idea of putting all of our
pieces on the D2 Knight is I think going
to lead to a very quick victory
so it's it's it's a matter of just
feeling when you can take material when
you can give a little bit of material
it's an art not a science it's how you
should think of it now how do we
actually get to this D2 Knight well
multiple ways that we can do this but
the straightforward move is again Bishop
G7 to H6 yes I said you should be
careful about leaving the fincarode
square but here there's a very good
reason for that and now
um
okay actually wait a second
we need to be a little bit careful here
I missed a small detail
I'm not that it matters I mean we're up
with freaking Queen
I honestly forgot that after Bishop G4
white can slide the king over to B1
and hilariously enough if we then take
the Knight on F3
if we then take the Knight on F3 the
knight from D2 actually can recapture
so I would propose a small amendment to
our idea
and rather than playing Bishop G4 let's
prevent the white king from moving to B1
because a moving Target is a lot harder
to put down
so we make a small Amendment we play
Bishop not the G4 but F5
right we just stopped the white king
from moving and we're also preparing to
activate our final piece with the Rook a
to C8 maybe some sacrifices on C3 we
also have a hidden mate threat which
white can prevent by bringing his own
Rook over to E1 but if he doesn't do
that hopefully we'll get a chance to
execute it yeah actually white is
helping us Checkmate the king what's
funny is that you might notice the move
Queen takes F3 exploiting the pin but if
I'm looking at this correctly there is
an even better move there is a move that
leads to Checkmate in two moves and it's
Queen to E4 yeah very good using the pin
so the night Queen is Untouchable but
the threat is Queen B1 made
because again the Knight is pinned right
just a classic mating pattern and I
don't think there's a defense that it's
nothing special I'm over hyping this but
still it's kind of nice
it's it's a pretty tactic because both
of these squares are quote unquote
defended by the Knight but because the
Knight is pinned here you see just the
pure power of of the pin in chess
but you say you would have never seen
that I think you can definitely see that
if you find yourself saying I would
never find such a move
you should ask yourself why like what
about this move makes it hard to see is
it the fact that you think this square
is defended or why do you think the
square is defended well it's the
underlying reason is probably because
you're underestimating the power of the
PIN
right and maybe you're too focused on
the free night
and so you should say to yourself okay
the next time I see like a free piece
I'm going to take another 15 20 seconds
and I'm going to consider the other
candidate moves Queen E4 Queen B1 is
mate because again the Knight cannot
capture the queen
because the Knight is pinned to the King
which I cannot draw this Arrow
that was a simple game
yeah if you see a good move look for a
better one
that was a simple straightforward game
our opponent got off on the wrong foot
with this weird D4 Queen takes D4 line
now to clarify what I said earlier
against D5 D4 is a legitimate move this
is the center game and if you run a
search you'll see that even a lot of top
GMS have played the center game it's an
offbeat opening right it's it's a second
rate opening but it's it's it's much
more legit than against the Sicilian and
I can go into why that is what the
difference is
uh but but just you can just take my
word for it like usually the queen drops
back to E3 actually
so
yeah against the Sicilian this this just
makes much much less sense
uh this is like a d a d tier opening I
think that probably white should keep
the queen in the center I think Queen A4
is another inaccuracy
okay so we played G6 still like if you
turn on the engine you will find that
the position is still close to equal
it's not like white is lost because he's
played two queen moves right that's not
how chess works but white has to be very
very accurate in order to keep the
balance and in order to keep the balance
I think white just needs to focus on
developing as quickly as possible White
had to go Knight F3 and Knight C3 and
Bishop E2 just get the pieces out and
castle kingside and I think here the
position is still basically borderline
equal
I would probably still take black but
nonetheless in Rook D1 the engine is
giving Bishop D7 and the engine is
giving this weird repetition
Queen B3 Knight A5 Queen B4 Knight C6
so
development was Paramount here Bishop D2
is a weird move
but at least white should have followed
up with Knight C3
the plan after Bishop C3 was not to play
E5 and weaken the D6 Square blunting the
bishop the plan of course was to just
play Knight F6 put the Knight between
the two Bishops
and a lot of people would be afraid of
this move but if you've paid attention
to this game you should know that Knight
D5 solves all of the problems very
neatly because it pressures the bishop
this is nothing to be afraid of you can
just play Knight takes C3
big whoop your King's on F7 for like an
instant
how should black proceed in this
position how do we solve the problem of
this King on F7 a good time to introduce
the concept of artificial castling or
castling by hand yeah you start by
putting the Rook on f8 so that when the
king drops back to G yay The Rook is not
out of the game you're literally
castling by hand and you're not fearing
this check because you can put the pawn
up on E6 and then follow up perhaps with
the move d7d5
but you have to be careful if White
Castles you should most definitely start
with King ji actually King G8 there
might be Bishop takes E6 check
so yeah you should first get the queen
out of d8 oh actually this this maybe
even wins The Pawn on G2 so uh but what
I was gonna say is you want to be very
careful about making a move like D5 as
long as the king is on F7 you have to be
careful of tactics like this
uh so so
in any case in any case
um
Bishop C3 was not scary C3 is definitely
not scary we go Knight F6 notice the
patience we castle and E5 just makes
things a million times worse
um but after something like Knight D2 We
ourselves would have played D5
and if white plays E5 then
at the very least Knight G4 wins The
Pawn on E5 three Defender three
attackers one Defender
and if white plays e takes D5 we would
have played Knight takes D5 with just a
massive initiative and already I'm
thinking of sacks on C3
and you know we don't even have to do
that we can just get our Bishop out to a
nice active Square
and after something like Knight gf3 we
can send the e-pawn down the board E5 E4
E3
and White's position is just totally
collapsing here
so that's all it takes right these these
two or three sloppy moves and already
white is with his back against the wall
but after E5 Knight D5 it's just lost I
think I think it's just borderline white
should have gone Bishop G3 here this was
maybe the last chance to keep some
chances alive
and what's interesting is that Knight
takes C5 is kind of a blunder
can anybody spot why Knight takes C5 is
sort of a semi-blunder black is still
better after this move but this
essentially loses a piece
so lpdo right you have two of these
undefended pieces on D5 and E5 I say
okay well what about a skewer what about
Queen B5
well that's not going to cut it because
here I can drop the Knight back to C7
and the issue is that the bishop defends
the other Knight the other Knight isn't
actually undefended but you can make it
undefended you start by taking that
Knight off of the board and the point is
just to make sure that you have these
two now these pieces are actually
undefended and you can Fork them right
two undefended pieces you'd be thinking
about forking Queen E4 Slide the queen
over attack both the same time the
Knight cannot defend the bishop Bishop
from the Nikes the knights on light
Square
so in fact black would be losing here
were it not for one counter resource so
let's say you blundered let's say you
blundered I think a lot of people
playing Black in this position would
panic and would probably play a move
like Knight takes C3 let's at least give
up the night for a pun but there is a
move that preserves an advantage for
black
right when you blunder like this you
should try to focus on what your assets
are and Black's greatest asset is his
lead in development
so we can try to
we can try to create a major counter
threat not with Queen A5 then Queen
takes C5 you have no discovery
the money you have no discovery
but you're close Queen B6 only moved to
keep the advantage Queen d8 to B6
attacking the B2 Pawn
can I create a very strong counter
threat
is the question you should be asking
yourself often when you've blundered
so for example Queen takes C5 you can
already play Queen's xp2
and I'm not convinced that black is
better here I think this is complicated
white has two pieces for a rook
and white is pretty close to completing
the development but at the very least
this doesn't lose a piece
does Knight B6 before Bishop takes E5
work no because the queen can move away
and simultaneously defend the bishop
that does not work
in any case Queen E4 of course just
loses the game I mean once white loses
the pawn and drops the bishop yeah Queen
C7 I really like I think this is a
really strong move
of course white should have dropped the
queen back to G3 and then we could have
just claimed the center with D5 and
played Bishop F5 and black is a pawn up
and totally dominating in the center
this is like minus four
but of course Knight T3 Chuck just wins
the queen so at this level unfortunately
players often fold very very quickly
when faced with these types of problems
but a good illustration of just the just
the importance of development honestly
you can just see why why people are so
obsessed with development why fast
accurate and active development is so
important if you neglect it you get
burned immediately and to burn someone
who's not developing all you really need
to know is develop your own pieces to
active squares and open the center
that's literally all we were planning to
do our opponent opened the center for us
with the movie five
okay so again most of the games we're
winning so far we're doing it by abiding
by these general principles to the
letter and being tactically alert to
potential tactical possibilities such as
of course the move Queen C7 right how
did I see this move well I noticed that
the White Queen is incredibly vulnerable
it's all alone the king is vulnerable
and you've got these combination of
these factors you already start looking
at forks and discoveries that you should
be primed to do that and we did it and
we won the queen won the game okay guys
hope you hope you enjoyed the games
stay tuned for more YouTube videos on
the speedrun and I will try to stream
tomorrow evening
all right everybody thanks for hanging
out today have a great start to your
weekend
and I'll see you all tomorrow bye
[Music]